<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Guillaume T. Vallet on Guillaume T. Vallet</title>
    <link>https://larlequin.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Guillaume T. Vallet on Guillaume T. Vallet</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>fr-fr</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Guillaume Vallet</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title> Sleep on your memory traces: How sleep effects can be explained by Act-In, a functional memory model</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2017/2017-mazza-somactin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 22:34:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2017/2017-mazza-somactin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Numerous studies have explored the effect of sleep on memory. It is well known that a period
of sleep, compared to a similar period of wakefulness, protects memories from interference,
improves performance, and might also reorganize memory traces in a way that encourages
creativity and rule extraction. It is assumed that these benefits come from the reactivation of
brain networks, mainly involving the hippocampal structure, as well as from their
synchronization with neocortical networks during sleep, thereby underpinning
sleep-dependent memory consolidation and reorganization. However, this memory
reorganization is difficult to explain within classical memory models. The present paper aims
to describe whether the influence of sleep on memory could be explained using a multiple
trace memory model that is consistent with the concept of embodied cognition: the Act-In
(activation-integration) memory model. We propose an original approach to the results
observed in sleep research on the basis of two simple mechanisms, namely activation and
integration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When the source of false memory helps to differentiate mild cognitive impairment from Alzheimer’s Disease</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/2017-vallet-escop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2017 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/2017-vallet-escop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background.&lt;/strong&gt; Episodic memory impairment is at the core of amnestic Mild Cognitive Impairment (aMCI) and Alzheimer’s Disease (AD). Notably, they both commit more memory errors than control participants. Nonetheless, these two groups of patients exhibit the same kinds of memory errors in recognition. The present study aims at exploring whether the source of the memory errors might help to distinguish aMCI from AD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Method.&lt;/strong&gt; Three groups of participants, 25 healthy elderly adults (HE), 20 aMCI patients and 9 AD patients, selectively learn 15 words (underlined) always presented with a distractor (not underlined).  Few minutes after, they complete a yes/no recognition task in which the targets are mixed with distractors. Half of the distractors comes from the learning phase (old condition) and the other half are new words (new condition). Old and new distractors could belong to the same category (close condition: kettle-coffe maker), or to a related category (kettle-herbal tea), or to a unrelated category (kettle-spinning top) as the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results.&lt;/strong&gt; As expected, HE show the best memory performance followed by the aMCI patients and finally the AD patients. The same pattern of results is observed for the memory errors in the new condition. However, aMCI and AD patients exhibit similar performance in the close condition. Reversely, the biggest gap in performance between these groups is reported in the old close distractor condition, whereas similar performance is shown in the other conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion.&lt;/strong&gt; The results suggest that both quantity and quality of memories should be taken into account in the evaluation of memory performance. AD patients present a more qualitatively impaired memory representation than aMCI patients (Vallet, Rouleau et al., 2016). This study highlights the usefulness of a selective learning procedure to distinguish between aMCI and AD as proposed in the binding memory test (Buschke, 2014).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keywords:&lt;/strong&gt; memory, alzheimer’s disease, mild cognitive impairment, source memory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Références.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Buschke, H. (2014) The rationale of the Memory Binding Test. In L.G. Nilsson, N. Ohta (Eds), &lt;em&gt;Dementia and Memory&lt;/em&gt; (pp. 55–71). Psychology Press: New York.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vallet, G. T., Rouleau, I., Benoit, S., Langlois, R., Barbeau, E. J., &amp;amp; Joubert, S. (2016). Alzheimer’s disease and memory strength: Gradual decline of memory traces as a function of their strength. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Clinical and Experimental Neuropsychology, 38&lt;/em&gt;(6), 648–660.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Différenciation du trouble cognitif léger et de la maladie d’Alzheimer grâce à la source des fausses reconnaissances.</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/2017-vallet-sfp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/2017-vallet-sfp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction.&lt;/strong&gt; Le trouble cognitif léger amnésique (TCL) et la maladie d’Alzheimer (MA) se caractérisent par une altération de la mémoire épisodique, tant en termes quantitatifs que qualitatifs. Cette altération se traduit notamment par une augmentation des erreurs de mémoire, qui semblent d’ailleurs à mêmes de distinguer ces troubles neurocognitifs d’autres formes (Hildebrandt, Haldenwanger, &amp;amp; Eling, 2009). Cependant, ces deux populations commettraient le même type d’erreurs, du moins lors de la reconnaissance. Cette étude explore si la source des erreurs de mémoire, à l’encodage ou à la récupération, permettrait de distinguer le TCL de la MA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matériel et méthode.&lt;/strong&gt; Trois groupes de participants, 25 personnes âgées (PA), 20 patients TCL et 9 patients MA, ont complété une tâche de mémoire verbale. Ils devaient apprendre sélectivement 15 mots (soulignés) qui étaient toujours présentés par paire avec un distracteur (non souligné). Il s’en suivait une tâche de reconnaissance oui/non, où les cibles à apprendre étaient mélangées avec des distracteurs, pour moitié ceux issus de la phase d’apprentissage (condition ancien) et pour moitié de nouveaux distracteurs (condition nouveau). Les anciens et les nouveaux distracteurs pouvaient soit appartenir à la même catégorie (condition proche : bouilloire-cafetière), soit être dans des catégories reliées (bouilloire-tisane) ou être non reliés aux cibles (bouilloire-toupie).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Résultats.&lt;/strong&gt;
Comme attendu, les PA présentent les meilleures performances suivies de patients MCI et enfin des patients MA. Ce dégradé de performance se retrouve globalement pour les erreurs de mémoire pour les distracteurs introduit lors de la reconnaissance (condition nouveau). Cependant, les patients TCL et MA ne se différencient pas pour les distracteurs les plus proches. À l’inverse, l’écart le plus important est constaté pour les distracteurs anciens proches, alors que les performances étaient similaires pour ceux non-reliés.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion.&lt;/strong&gt;
Les résultats indiquent que la quantité et la qualité des souvenirs sont à prendre en compte dans l’évaluation des capacités mnésiques. Les patients MA semblent présenter une atteinte mnésique qualitivement plus dégradée que les TCL (Vallet, Rouleau, Benoit, Langlois, Barbeau, &amp;amp; Joubert, 2016). Cette étude souligne l’intérêt d’un apprentissage sélectif pour différencier le degré d’atteinte de la mémoire tel que constaté entre des patients TCL et MA. Cette mémoire de source, intégrative, est d’ailleurs supposée plus sensible pour détecter précocement les atteintes mnésiques (Buschke, 2014).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Références.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Buschke, H. (2014) The rationale of the Memory Binding Test. In L.G. Nilsson, N. Ohta (Eds), &lt;em&gt;Dementia and Memory&lt;/em&gt; (pp. 55–71). Psychology Press: New York.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hildebrandt, H., Haldenwanger, A., &amp;amp; Eling, P. (2009). False recognition helps to distinguish patients with Alzheimer’s disease and amnestic MCI from patients with other kinds of dementia. &lt;em&gt;Dementia and Geriatric Cognitive Disorders, 28&lt;/em&gt;(2), 159–167.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vallet, G. T., Rouleau, I., Benoit, S., Langlois, R., Barbeau, E. J., &amp;amp; Joubert, S. (2016). Alzheimer’s disease and memory strength: Gradual decline of memory traces as a function of their strength. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Clinical and Experimental Neuropsychology, 38&lt;/em&gt;(6), 648–660.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> A SEMantic and EPisodic Memory Test (SEMEP) Developed Within the Embodied Cognition Framework: Application to Normal Aging, Alzheimer’s Disease and Semantic Dementia</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2017/2017-vallet-semep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2017 22:34:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2017/2017-vallet-semep/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embodiment has highlighted the importance of sensory-motor components in cognition.
Perception and memory are thus very tightly bound together, and episodic and semantic
memories should rely on the same groundedmemory traces. Reduced perception should
then directly reduce the ability to encode and retrieve an episodic memory, as in normal
aging. Multimodal integration deficits, as in Alzheimer’s disease, should lead to more
severe episodic memory impairment. The present study introduces a new memory test
developed to take into account these assumptions. The SEMEP (SEMantic-Episodic)
memory test proposes to assess conjointly semantic and episodic knowledge across
multiple tasks: semantic matching, naming, free recall, and recognition. The performance
of young adults is compared to healthy elderly adults (HE), patients with Alzheimer’s
disease (AD), and patients with semantic dementia (SD). The results show specific
patterns of performance between the groups. HE commit memory errors only for
presented but not to be remembered items. AD patients present the worst episodic
memory performance associated with intrusion errors (recall or recognition of items
never presented). They were the only group to not benefit from a visual isolation
(addition of a yellow background), a method known to increase the distinctiveness of the
memory traces. Finally, SD patients suffer from the most severe semantic impairment.
To conclude, confusion errors are common across all the elderly groups, whereas AD
was the only group to exhibit regular intrusion errors and SD patients to show severe
semantic impairment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ageism among psychology students: A comparative analysis between Belgium and Quebec (Canada)</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2017/2017-marquet-agism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 22:34:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2017/2017-marquet-agism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study was to investigate the comprehension of concrete, abstract and abstract emotional words in semantic variant primary progressive aphasia (svPPA), Alzheimer’s disease (AD), and healthy elderly adults (HE) Three groups of participants (9 svPPA, 12 AD, 11 HE) underwent a general neuropsychological assessment, a similarity judgment task, and structural brain MRI. The three types of words were processed similarly in the group of AD participants. In contrast, patients in the svPPA group were significantly more impaired at processing concrete words than abstract words, while comprehension of abstract emotional words was in between. VBM analyses showed that comprehension of concrete words relative to abstract words was significantly correlated with atrophy in the left anterior temporal lobe. These results support the view that concrete words are disproportionately impaired in svPPA, and that concrete and abstract words may rely upon partly dissociable brain regions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comprehension of concrete and abstract words in semantic variant primary progressive aphasia and Alzheimer’s disease: a behavioral and neuroimaging study</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2017/2017-sven-abscon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 22:34:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2017/2017-sven-abscon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study was to investigate the comprehension of concrete, abstract and abstract emotional words in semantic variant primary progressive aphasia (svPPA), Alzheimer’s disease (AD), and healthy elderly adults (HE) Three groups of participants (9 svPPA, 12 AD, 11 HE) underwent a general neuropsychological assessment, a similarity judgment task, and structural brain MRI. The three types of words were processed similarly in the group of AD participants. In contrast, patients in the svPPA group were significantly more impaired at processing concrete words than abstract words, while comprehension of abstract emotional words was in between. VBM analyses showed that comprehension of concrete words relative to abstract words was significantly correlated with atrophy in the left anterior temporal lobe. These results support the view that concrete words are disproportionately impaired in svPPA, and that concrete and abstract words may rely upon partly dissociable brain regions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>L’impact des plaques bêta-amyloïdes sur la cognition: au-delà de l’âge et de l’éducation</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/2017-lavall%C3%A9e-cernec/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 20:26:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/2017-lavall%C3%A9e-cernec/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Un corps puis un esprit : comment le corps modifie nos pensées !</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/2017-corpscerveau/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/2017-corpscerveau/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The automatic visual simulation of words: A memory reactivated mask slows down conceptual access</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2017/2017-embodied-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 22:34:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2017/2017-embodied-words/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How do we represent the meaning of words? The present study assesses whether access to conceptual knowledge requires the reenactment of the sensory components of a concept. The reenactment—that is, simulation—was tested in a word categorisation task using an innovative masking paradigm. We hypothesised that a meaningless reactivated visual mask should interfere with the simulation of the visual dimension of concrete words. This assumption was tested in a paradigm in which participants were not aware of the link between the visual mask and the words to be processed. In the first phase, participants created a tone–visual mask or tone–control stimulus association. In the test phase, they categorised words that were presented with 1 of the tones. Results showed that words were processed more slowly when they were presented with the reactivated mask. This interference effect was only correlated with and explained by the value of the visual perceptual strength of the words (i.e., our experience with the visual dimensions associated with concepts) and not with other characteristics. We interpret these findings in terms of word access, which may involve the simulation of sensory features associated with the concept, even if participants were not explicitly required to access visual properties.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gcushen.github.io/hugo-academic-demo/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Editorial: Dynamics of sensorimotor interactions in embodied cognition</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2016/2016-edito_frontiers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 17:54:08 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2016/2016-edito_frontiers/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alzheimer’s disease and memory strength: Gradual decline of memory traces as a function of their strength</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2016/2016-dms48/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2016 22:34:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2016/2016-dms48/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Objective:&lt;/em&gt; Episodic memory impairment is at the core of amnestic mild cognitive impair- ment (aMCI) and Alzheimer’s disease (AD). The origin of memory deficits may result either from an encoding deficit or from an accelerated decline of the memory trace. The present study explores these two hypotheses.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Method:&lt;/em&gt; We used the delayed-matching-to sample 48 items (DMS-48) memory test in a group of controls, aMCI patients, and AD patients (n= 16 in each group). The DMS-48 offers an incidental learning phase followed by three forced-choice recognition tests at three-minute, one-hour, and one-week delays. Moreover, the forced-choice test distinguishes three kinds of couple items: abstract (meaningless), paired (two similar exemplars), and unique (two different objects) items.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Results:&lt;/em&gt; As predicted by the accelerated forgetting hypothesis, patients showed a decrease in recognition performance over time. Controls also exhibited a similar decline in performance. As predicted by the encoding deficit hypothesis, abstract items were the most poorly recognized in AD, at both the three-minute and the one-week delays. In AD, recognition of the paired items also dropped after the one-hour delay, followed by unique items after a one-week delay. Patients with aMCI exhibited a performance that was similar to controls, except for abstract items, which dropped at the one-week delay.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/em&gt; These results are discussed in light of a third hypothesis, the memory strength hypothesis, in order to better account for the progressive decline in memory performance as a function of the item type in AD.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Qualitative impairment in face perception in Alzheimer’s Disease: Evidence from a reduced face inversion effect</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2016/2016-alz-faces/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2016 14:55:29 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2016/2016-alz-faces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prevalent face recognition difficulties in Alzheimer’s disease (AD) have typically been attributed to the underlying episodic and semantic memory impairment. The aim of the current study was to determine if AD patients are also impaired at the perceptual level for faces, more specifically at extracting a visual representation of an individual face. To address this question, we investigated the matching of simultaneously presented individual faces and of other nonface familiar shapes (cars), at both upright and inverted orientation, in a group of mild AD patients and in a group of healthy older controls matched for age and education. AD patients showed a reduced inversion effect (i.e., larger performance for upright than inverted stimuli) for faces, but not for cars, both in terms of error rates and response times. While healthy participants showed a much larger decrease in performance for faces than for cars with inversion, the inversion effect did not differ significantly for faces and cars in AD. This abnormal inversion effect for faces was observed in a large subset of individual patients with AD. These results suggest that AD patients have deficits in higher-level visual processes, more specifically at perceiving individual faces, a function that relies on holistic representations specific to upright face stimuli. These deficits, combined with their memory impairment, may contribute to the difficulties in recognizing familiar people that are often reported in patients suffering from the disease and by their caregivers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Normative data for phonemic and semantic verbal fluency test in the adult French–Quebec population and validation study in Alzheimer’s disease and depression</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2016/2016-norm_fluences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2016 17:49:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2016/2016-norm_fluences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OBJECTIVE: Verbal fluency tasks are principally used to assess lexical access and have shown usefulness for differential diagnosis. The purpose of Study 1 was to provide normative data in the adult French-Quebec population (Canada) for semantic verbal fluency (animals), for two sets of phonemic verbal fluency (TNP and PFL), and for letter P alone (60 seconds per category/letter). The objectives of Study 2 were to establish the diagnostic and predictive validity of the present tasks and normative data in Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (AD) and major depressive episode (MDE). METHOD: The normative sample consisted of 932 participants aged 19-91 years. Based on multiple linear regressions, equations to calculate Z-scores were provided. To assess validity, performance of 62 healthy participants was compared to 62 participants with AD and 41 with MDE aged over 50. RESULTS: Age and education, but not gender, predicted performance on each verbal fluency task. Healthy adults aged 50 and younger had a better performance on semantic than phonemic verbal fluency. In comparison to MDE, AD participants had lower performance on animals and TNP, but not on letter P. Ninety percent of people with a Z-score &amp;lt;/= -1.50 on semantic verbal fluency had AD and the global accuracy was 76.6%. Test-retest reliability over one year was high for both animals (r = .711) and TNP (r = .790) in healthy older participants, but dropped for animals in people with AD (r = .493). CONCLUSIONS: These data will strengthen accurate detection of verbal fluency deficits in French-Quebec adults.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Des objets sans sens : connaissances concrètes et démence sémantique</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/2016-cernec/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/talk/2016-cernec/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objectif:&lt;/strong&gt; Cette étude évalue si des connaissances concrètes, abstraites, et émotionnelles sont atteintes de manière différente dans la démence sémantique.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Méthodologie:&lt;/strong&gt; 9 patients souffrant de démence sémantique (DS), 12 patients souffrant de la maladie d’Alzheimer (MA) et 11 personnes âgées contrôles ont complété une tâche d’appariement sémantique. Parmi trois mots affichés, ils devaient décider quels mots formaient la meilleure paire au niveau sémantique. Les triades réfèraient soit à des connaissances concrètes (lit/chaise/sofa), abstraites (ex. opinion/avis/intérêt) ou émotionnelles (nostalgie/joie/bonheur).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Résultats:&lt;/strong&gt; Les patients DS présentent les performances les plus faibles avec un déficit particulièrement important pour les triades de mots concrets. Les patients MA performent mieux que les patients DS, mais ne montrent aucune différence entre les conditions. Finalement, les contrôles présentent de meilleures performances pour les émotionnels. Ces résultats corroborent l’hypothèse d’un effet inverse de concrétude dans la DS pour la première fois dans une étude de groupe pour des noms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
