<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>1 on Guillaume T. Vallet</title>
    <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication_types/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 1 on Guillaume T. Vallet</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>fr-fr</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Guillaume Vallet</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2011 07:56:40 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/publication_types/1/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Sensory-dependent nature of audio-visual interactions for semantic knowledge</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2011/2011-proceed-actis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2011 07:56:40 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2011/2011-proceed-actis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The nature of audio-visual interactions is poorly understood for meaningful objects. These interactions would be indirect through semantic memory according to the amodal nature of knowledge, whereas these interactions would be direct accord- ing to the modal nature of knowledge. This question, cen- tral for both memory and multisensory frameworks, was as- sessed using a cross-modal priming paradigm from auditory to visual modalities tested on familiar objects. For half of the sound primes, a visual abstract mask was simultaneously pre- sented to the participants. The results showed a cross-modal priming effect for semantically congruent objects compared to semantically incongruent objects presented without the mask. The mask interfered in the semantically congruent condition, but had no effect in the semantically incongruent condition. The semantic specificity of the mask effect demonstrates a memory-related effect. The results suggest that audio-visual interactions are direct. The data support the modal approach of knowledge and the grounded cognition theory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Sensory nature of knowledge: Generalization vs . specification mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2010/2010-brunel-proceeding-episem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2010 09:16:25 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://larlequin.github.io/publication/2010/2010-brunel-proceeding-episem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The aim of the present study was to show the perceptual nature of conceptual knowledge and the dialectic between conceptual and episodic knowledge. We used an original paradigm adapted from Brunel, Labeye, Lesourd, Versace study (in press) . This paradigm is divided into three phases. The first one consists in learning a variable association between a geometrical shape and a white noise. The second phase consists in a short- term priming paradigm where a prime shape (either associated or not with a sound in the first phase) preceded a pure tone. The participants have to categorize this sound as low-pitched or high- pitched sound. At least, the third phase consists in a recognition phase about the learning phase. The results have provided evidence supporting the assumption that memory mechanisms are not dissociated from perceptual mechanisms. Moreover, through the manipulation of the shape/sound association in the learning phase, we have demonstrated that generalization mechanism allowed a stimulus to benefit from the feature belonging to its category, whereas specification mechanism allowed a stimulus to keep its specificity compared to the category.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
